A Guide to the JMU Architectural Drawings Collection, 1914-1983
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
JMU Architectural Drawings Collection1914-1983
Special Collections, James Madison University
FM 2006-1207
One 44" x 6 1/2" x 6 1/2 box, Two 40" x 32" folders; 7 linear feet
The JMU Architectural Drawings Collection, 1914-1983, (7 linear feet), is comprised of blue prints, pencil tracings, and linen drawings of various JMU buildings, their corresponding mechanical systems, and campus grounds.
Various
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from JMU's Facilities Management Engineering Department in 2006.
Provenance
The Harrisonburg High School drawings became property of James Madison University after the university purchased the high school in 2006.
Biographical Information
Due to the artificial nature of this collection, a historical note is not applicable. Reference bibliography for further historical information pertaining to specific campus buildings.
Scope and Content
The JMU Architectural Drawings Collection, 1914-1983, (7 linear feet), is comprised of blueprints, pencil tracings, and linen drawings of various JMU buildings, their corresponding mechanical systems, and campus grounds. The collection contains architectural plans of Alumnae Hall, Miller Hall, Harrisonburg High School, the Students' Building, the Practice House, and the Home Economics Building and topographic drawings of the university campus. The plans were created on four different surfaces, including pencil on linen, ink on linen, pencil on tracing paper, and carbon copy paper.
Arrangement
The arrangement is in 7 series, grouped by the building depicted in the drawings. Within each series the items are separated by the material, and the description of the drawings and their size. The carbon copies are placed in an oversized architectural box. Linen drawings of campus buildings are separated from plans of the mechanical systems in the Harrisonburg High School building. The arrangement of the series is as follows:
I: Madison College
II: Dormitory #5
III: Student's Building (Harrison Hall)
IV: Practice House (Varner House) & Home Economics Building (Moody Hall)
V: Miller Hall
VI: Alumnae Hall
VII: Harrisonburg High School (Memorial Hall)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Dingledine, Raymond C. Madison College: The First Fifty Years, 1908-1958. Harrisonburg, Va.: James Madison University, 1959.
http://leo.jmu.edu/record=b1149362~S0
James Madison University Major Buildings
http://www.jmu.edu/centennialcelebration/major_buildings.shtml
Jones, Nancy Bondurant. Rooted on Bluestone Hill: A History of James Madison University. Santa Fe and Staunton, Va.: Center for American Places, 2004.
http://leo.jmu.edu/record=b1847473~S0
Contents List
- Madison College
  - Topography, Madison College, 04/01/1940, blueprint
    ‐Architect: VA State Planning Board
  - Madison College, blueprint
  - Topography, Madison College, 04/01/1940, blueprint
  - Control Surveys and Monuments, 03/26/1940, blueprint
    ‐Architect: Commonwealth of Virginia, Section of Institutional Engineering
- Dormitory #5
  - Dormitory #5; Front Elevation, 04/01/1926, blueprint
    ‐Architect: Charles M. Robinson
- Students' Building (Harrison Hall)
  - Students' Building; Front and Side Elevation, 4/1/14, blueprint
- Practice House (Varner House); Home Economics Building (Moody Hall)
  - Basement Floor Plan, 11/22/58, blueprint
    ‐Architect: Walford & Wright
  - First Floor Plan, 11/22/58, blueprint
  - Second Floor Plan, 11/22/58, blueprint
  - Front Elevation, 11/22/58, blueprint
  - Left-Side Elevation; Rear Elevation, 11/22/58, blueprint
  - Food Laboratory No.1 Layout, blueprint
  - Food Laboratory No. 3 Layout, blueprint
  - Basement Plan, 05/05/1928, blueprint
  - First Floor Plan, 05/05/1928, blueprint
  - Second Floor Plan, 05/05/1928, blueprint
  - Attic Plan, 05/05/1928, blueprint
  - Food Laboratory 203, 03/28/1960, blueprint
  - Food Laboratory 203, 03/28/1960, blueprint
  - Food Laboratory 201, 03/28/1960, blueprint
  - Floor Plan Food Lab #201, 03/29/1960, blueprint
  - Food Laboratory 202, 03/31/1960, blueprint
  - Food Laboratory 202, 03/31/1960, blueprint
  - Kitchen 211, 10/06/1960, blueprint
  - Textile Laboratory 109, 10/06/1960, blueprint
  - Related Arts Classroom No. 20, 10/10/1960, blueprint
  - Clothing Laboratory 107, 10/10/1960, blueprint
  - Basement Floor Plan, date of drawing unkown; stamped date 6/19/1969, blueprint
    ‐Architect: D'earcy P. Davis and Associates, Clyde E. McClintock
  - Floor Plan, 6/9/1969; stamped date 6/19/1969, blueprint
  - Equipment & Utility Schedule, 6/9/1969; stamped date 6/19/1969, blueprint
  - Basement Floor Plan; First Floor Plan; Finish Schedule; Door Schedule, June, 1960, blueprint
  - Second Floor Plan; Attic & Roof Plan; etc., June 1960, blueprint
  - Lounge, tracing, pencil
  - Room 210, 212, 213, 217, tracing, pencil
- Miller Hall
  - Miller Hall completion - East End; Entrance at Southeast corner of building, 03/03/1983, linen, pencil
    ‐Architect: drawn by D.P.D.
  - Miller Hall completion - East End; Details, 03/03/1983, linen, pencil
  - Miller Hall completion - East End; Elevation and Section, 03/03/1983, linen, pencil
- Alumnae Hall
  - Alumnae Hall; Front Elevation, 05/01/1921, ink on linen
- Harrisonburg High School (Memorial Hall)
  - Smoke Pipe Harrisonburg, tracing, pencil
  - Plan Showing the Position of Motor Base, 04/26/1928, tracing, pencil
    ‐Architect: American Heating and Ventilating Company
  - Section Thru Fan Room Showing Fresh Air Partition, 04/02/1928, tracing, pencil
    ‐Architect: L. W. L.
  - End View Showing Partition in Suspended Ceiling over Vent Shaft, 04/27/1928, tracing, pencil
  - Detail Showing Position of Ducts in Plenum Space, tracing, pencil
  - Plan of a Six-Stall Urinal, 12/23/1927, tracing, pencil
    ‐Architect: I.
  - Instructions for Heating Plant Operation, Harrisonburg High School, list
  - Plan for Ductworks Superimposed on Floor Plan (not titled), ink on linen
  - Ground Floor Plan, 1/27/1928, ink on linen
    ‐Architect: W.B.
  - 1st Floor Plan, 1/10/1928, ink on linen
    ‐Architect: L.W.L., retraced by W.A.B.
  - 2nd Floor Plan, 1/19/1927, ink on linen
  - Plan for Duct Work (But no title), 1/13/1928, ink on linen
  - Ground Floor Plan With Schedule of Heat and Vent Openings, 11/08/1927, tracing, pencil
    ‐Architect: O.M.N.
  - 1st Floor Plan, 1/10/1928, tracing, pencil
    ‐Architect: L.W.L.
  - 2nd Floor Plan, 1/19/1927, tracing, pencil
  - Addition to Present Building, 9/13/1934, tracing, pencil
    ‐Architect: S.
  - Revised Changing Location fo Boiler, 1/13/1928, tracing, pencil
  - Damper Details, 7/15/1929, tracing, pencil
    ‐Architect: W.A.B.
  - Plan of Reinforced Twenty GABI Top, tracing, pencil